Guide to the Vicki Hearne Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Vicki Hearne papers
1920-2005
1976-2001
YCAL MSS 250
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
20.35
(45 boxes)
The Vicki Hearne Papers consist of correspondence, writings, personal papers, photographs, audiocassettes, and clippings that document the development of her writing, from her works of poetry in the 1970s, through the books and articles she wrote in defense of dogs at the turn of the twenty-first century. Her writings reveal the connection between her work as an animal trainer and as an author and poet, both vocations informed by her readings and interpretation of philosophers including Plato, Nietzsche, and Wittgenstein. Drafts of many of her works of poetry, non-fiction, and her book of fiction reveal the evolution of the works, and notes and comments by editors regarding works submitted for publication illustrate the nature of her relationship with her publishers. Letters from colleagues and friends, particularly her mentor, John Hollander, provide insight into the support she received from those individuals.
Hearne, Vicki, 1946-2001
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Vicki Hearne, 2002, and gift of James Hearne, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 42-43: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 44: Restricted until January 1, 2060. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Vicki Hearne (1946-2001)
Victoria Elizabeth Hearne was born in Austin, Texas, on February 13, 1946, and grew up in a military family in Texas, Louisiana, and Mississippi. Hearne began her dog and horse training career in California in 1967, after learning she had a talent for the work when she trained her own dog under the mentorship of Hollywood animal trainers Bill and Dick Koehler. She continued to work with animals throughout her life. Having written poetry since her childhood, she studied writing and received a B.A. in English from the University of California, Riverside, in 1969. Hearne's published collections of poetry include Nervous Horses (1980), In the Absence of Horses (1983) and The Parts of Light (1994). Individual poems written by Hearne were published in magazines and journals including The New Republic, The Partisan Review, and Poetry. She was a Stegner Fellow in Poetry at Stanford University, and received a writing grant from the Ingram Merrill Foundation. In 1984, she was given the Peter I. B. Lavan Younger Poets Award from the Academy of American Poets. She taught creative writing at the University of California at Riverside from 1980 to 1984. From 1984 to 1986, she was an assistant professor of English at Yale, and she was a visiting fellow at the Institution for Social and Policy Studies at Yale from 1989 to 1995. Following her move to the Northeast, Hearne continued to train dogs at Silver Trails: The Animal Inn in Westbrook, Connecticut. Vicki Hearne and her first husband (from whom she was divorced in 1970) were the parents of a daughter, Colleen Lerman. Hearne married Robert Tragesser, a professor of philosophy, in 1983. She died of lung cancer in Branford, Connecticut on August 21, 2001.
Hearne's writing was informed by her work with dogs and horses and the philosophies of Plato, Nietzsche, and Wittgenstein, among others. She addressed issues of animal behavior and the ways in which animals communicate with humans in her books of nonfiction and in magazine and journal articles. She authored Adam's Task: Calling Animals by Name and Animal Happiness, and co-authored the book Horse Breaking: The Obedience Method with Bill Forest. Her articles "Talking With Dogs, Chimps and Others," and "How to Say Fetch," were published in Raritan in the early 1980s. She was published in American magazines including The Atlantic Monthly, Harper's, and The New Yorker, and in foreign publications including the Japanese edition of Esquire Magazine.
An ardent defender of breeds of dogs labeled by legal authorities as innately dangerous, Hearne served as an expert witness on dog behavior beginning in the 1980s. Her experiences while defending a dog (mistakenly identified as a pit bull) that had been sentenced to death for his biting offences in Stamford, Connecticut, were the subject of her book, Bandit: Dossier of a Dangerous Dog. After being granted custody of the dog for three months Hearne rehabilitated Bandit and was given permanent guardianship of the animal. She appeared in various media, gained an international following, and wrote numerous articles in which she spoke against city ordinances that banned particular breeds of dogs. The events surrounding the Bandit case were also chronicled in a documentary film, A Little Vicious, which was nominated for an Academy Award in 1992.
Scope and Contents
The Vicki Hearne Papers consist of correspondence, writings, personal papers, photographs, audiotapes, and clippings. The papers span the years 1920 through 2005, with the bulk of the material dating from 1976 through 2001. Hearne's papers document the development of her writing, from her works of poetry in the 1970s, through the books and articles she wrote in defense of dogs at the turn of the twenty-first century. Her writings reveal the connection between two seemingly separate endeavors--her work as an animal trainer and as an author and poet--both vocations informed by her readings and interpretation of philosophers including Plato, Nietzsche, and Wittgenstein. Drafts of many of her works of poetry, non-fiction, and her book of fiction reveal the evolution of the works, and notes and comments by editors regarding works submitted for publication illustrate the nature of her relationship with her publishers. Letters from colleagues and friends, particularly her mentor, John Hollander, provide insight into the support she received from those individuals. Files relating to animal training and the material accompanying the drafts of her writings, particularly the Bandit case correspondence, case files, and clipping files, reveal her professional and personal connection to her own companion animals and to those of her friends and colleagues. While Hearne made her position on animal training, behavior, and rights clear in her writings, the research and clipping files provide additional background information on the subjects, and document the various points of view among law enforcement and legislators, members of various animal rights organizations, and dog trainers and breeders. Letters from dog breeders (particularly Roselma Elliot) with whom she had professional and personal relationships document not only the business of breeding and selling of dogs, but behaviorial and health issues of animals owned by Hearne and others as well.
Arrangement
Organized into five series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1976-2001. II. Writings, 1969-2001. III. Animal Records and Training Files, 1989-2001. IV. Personal Papers, 1920-2001. V. Photographs and Audiotapes, 1955-1992. 2008 Addition, 1983-2005.
Animal rights activists -- United States -- Archives; Animal trainers -- United States -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Dogs -- Behavior; Horses -- Training; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographs; Hearne, Vicki, 1946-2001; Hollander, John, 1929-2013
- Correspondence, 1976-2001; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Incoming, Outgoing, and Third Party, and dates from 1976 to 2001. With the exception of letters from unidentified correspondents, which are arranged chronologically, the letters are arranged alphabetically within each subseries.
  Scope and Contents
  The majority of the incoming correspondence consists of letters received by Hearne regarding animal training and breeding, and the publication of her writings. Personal letters from family members include those from her daughter, Colleen Lerman, her brother Jim Hearne, and her mother, Elizabeth Hearne. Letters from her friend and mentor, John Hollander, and those written to Hearne by Roselma Elliott, a breeder of Airedales with whom Hearne became friends, form the largest groups of letters from individual correspondents. Outgoing correspondence consists of one folder of copies of letters regarding publications, including a letter to the editor of Harper's, Lewis Lapham, and a letter to Iris Murdoch regarding a proposed anthology. Several unsent mailings include a letter to her daughter. Third-party correspondence includes notes and letters sent to Robert Tragesser following Hearne's death in 2001. Drafts of letters written by Hearne may be found in the spiral notebooks in Series II. Additional correspondence regarding the Bandit case may be found in Series II.
  - Incoming
    - "A" general, 1976-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1992-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Anthony, Wendy, 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Atlantic Monthly, 1983, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Atlantic Monthly Press, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "B" general, 1985-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "C" general, 1981-2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cohen, Margory, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Common Knowledge, 1991-2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cooper, Diana, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "D" general, 1975-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Defler, Julie, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "E" general, 1985-1997 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Elliott, Roselma, 1985-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Elliott, Roselma, 1985-1997, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-20)
    - "F" general, 1983-2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "G" general, 1986-2001 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "H" general, 1986-2001 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - HarperCollins Publishers, 1991, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Harper's Magazine, 1983-1997 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Hearne, Elizabeth, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Hearne, Jim, 1981-2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Hollander, John, 1976-2001,undated (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
    - Holt, Steele, 1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "I" - "J" general, 1985-1994 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Johnson, Henry, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Johnson, Ruth, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "K" - "L" general, 1984-2001 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Lerman, Colleen, 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "M" general, 1980-1999, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Martin, David, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - "N" - "P" general, 1984-2001, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - The New Yorker, 1976-1997 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Princeton University Press, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - "R" general, 1984-1998 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Random House, Inc., 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Raritan: A Quarterly Review, 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Regan, Tom, 1984, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Robert Cornfield Literary Agency, 1988-1991 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Rosenfeld, Mordecai, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "S" general, 1976-2001, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Schroeder, Bethany, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - "T" - "V" general, 1983-2001, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - University of Western Ontario, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - University of Southern California School of Urban and Regional Planning, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - "W" - "Z" general, 1986-1998 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Wallace & Sheil Literary Agency, 1983-1987 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Wallace Literary Agency, 1988-1991 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Walsh, Mike, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Yale Center for British Art, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Yale University, 1983-1993 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Correspondents identified by first name, B-T, 1980-2001, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Unidentified correspondents, 1985-2001 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Empty envelopes (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Outgoing
    - "A" - "S" and unidentified, 1983-1991, 2001, undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Third Party, 1989, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 63)
- Writings, 1969-2001; Series II; 13.14; (32 boxes)
  This series is organized into seven subseries: Books, Articles and Presentations, Book Reviews, Short Stories and Plays, Poetry, Miscellaneous Writings, and Writings by Others. Within each subseries the material is arranged alphabetically by title or author.
  This series includes writings by Hearne and others dating from 1969 to 2001. Single drafts of titles are described individually. Titles represented by several drafts are described as "multiple drafts," and may include: typescript and holograph drafts, in original, photocopy, and mimeographed form, corrected by Hearne, and containing annotations by editors and proofreaders' marks. Additional materials include page proofs, contracts with publishers, cover letters, research files, publicity material, and reviews. Published versions of some of the magazine and journal articles are also included.
  The subseries Books, consists of materials dating from 1984-2000, and includes various drafts of her published non-fiction works, Adams Task: Calling Animals by Name, Animal Happiness, Bandit: Dossier of a Dangerous Dog, and the work she co-authored with Bill Forest, Horse Breaking: The Obedience Method, as well as her novel, The White German Shepherd. Drafts of an unpublished work, "First Friend," are also included. The Bandit -related materials include research files, correspondence, case files, and other case documentation, as well as copies of the National "Pit Bull Terrier" Defense Association Newsletter, which she published in 1988-1989 to inform her friends and supporters of developments in the case.
  The subseries Articles and Presentations, consists of drafts and published versions of works dating from 1982-2000, and includes her writings for journals and magazines, including the weekly "Animals" column she wrote for The Los Angeles Times Magazine from 1985 to 1986. While the majority of articles focus on issues of animal behavior and training, the subseries also contains material on other topics, including an obituary for her mentor William Koehler, and a draft of a biographical essay on her mother, "Ornery."
  The subseries Book Reviews, contains Hearne's reviews of books on various animal-related subjects published in the The New York Times Book Review from 1984 to 1990.
  The subseries Short Stories and Plays, consists of several stories including "The Spine of Eclipse"; "The Problem of Belief," written with her husband Robert Tragesser; and a play, "Fido: Play in 3 Strophes." While "Spine of Eclipse" is dated 1994, the other material is undated.
  The subseries Poetry, consists of materials relating to her published poetry collections, including Nervous Horses and In the Absence of Horses, as well as files containing drafts of additional collections and individual poems, dating from the 1970s to 2001. The series contains a section of Other Poems, which consists of material that was removed from loose-leaf binders and hanging file folders for preservation purposes, but kept in the arrangement in which it was found within the original housing. Folder titles were transcribed from binders or labeled according to title or subject of poems. Folders of miscellaneous drafts of poetry may contain typescript and holograph drafts, in original, photocopy, and mimeographed form, corrected and/or annotated by Hearne or others.
  The subseries Miscellaneous Writings, contains material removed from loose-leaf binders, spiral-bound notebooks, and folders for preservation purposes, and dates from 1981 to 2001. Binders were assigned numbers for ease of retrieval. The original order has been maintained as much as possible. In addition to the material listed, binders may contain various holograph and typescript notes, lists, mailing addresses, telephone numbers, etc. The spiral-bound notebooks contain a variety of writings, notes, anagrams, drafts of letters, addresses and telephone numbers, drawings and doodles, etc. Loose material found within the notebooks has been placed behind the notebook in each folder. Notebooks containing a predominant genre or topic are labeled as such and are filed in front of notebooks whose contents are more varied.
  The subseries Writings of Others, consists of drafts, off-prints, and photocopies of published works by friends and other writers including Robert Tragesser, John Hollander, Harold Bloom, and Jorge Luis Borges, and date from 1972 to 2001.
  - Books
    - Adam's Task: Calling Animals by Name
      - Contracts, 1984, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - Chapters
        - "By Way of Explanation," multiple drafts, 1984, undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
        - "A Walk With Washoe: How Far Can We Go?" draft, typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
        - "How to Say, 'Fetch'," multiple drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 67-70)
        - "Tracking," multiple drafts, accompanied by letter to Hearne from [B----y?] dated 9/2/84, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 71-72)
        - "Crazy Horses," multiple drafts and corrected table of contents, undated (Box 5, Folder 73-75)
        - "Notes On the Obedience Horse," multiple drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
        - "Lo, the American (Pit) Bull Terrier," multiple drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
        - "The Thing About Cats," multiple drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
        - "Rights, Autism, and the Rougher Magics," draft with table of contents for Calling Animals by Name, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 79)
        - "A Plea for Harshness," multiple drafts, accompanied by letter from Hearne's editor, 1984 Apr 3 (Box 5, Folder 80)
        - "Animals, Language and What It's All For," [working title of volume], draft, typescript, with editor's annotations, undated (Box 6, Folder 81-85)
      - Page proofs, bound, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 86)
      - Royalty statements, 1987-1990 (Box 6, Folder 87)
      - Reviews, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 88)
      - Advertisement, undated (Box 6)
    - Animal Happiness (Box 6)
      - Contract with HarperCollins Publishers, Inc., for "Animal Portraits", 1991 (Box 7, Folder 89)
      - "Chapter 3, Companion Dog Excellent," multiple drafts, n.d., accompanied by letter containing comments from Diana Cooper, postmarked 2/26/2001 (Box 7, Folder 90-91)
      - Page proofs, bound, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 92)
      - Review, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 93)
      - Issue of Elle magazine, with article about Hearne and Animal Happiness, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - Bandit: Dossier of a Dangerous Dog
      - Background Materials and Research Notes
        - Bandit legal case files, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 95-99)
        - Correspondence, 1988-1991, undated (Box 7, Folder 100)
        - Red binder containing case background information, 1985-1988 (Box 8, Folder 101-102)
        - Journal and periodical articles, 1981-1993 (Box 8, Folder 103)
        - Court cases, 1987-1991 (Box 8, Folder 104)
        - Laws and legislation, 1986-1991 (Box 8, Folder 105)
        - Leof v. Tresan, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 106)
        - Pedigree searches, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 107-109)
      - Contract with HarperCollins Publishers, Inc., 1990 (Box 8, Folder 110)
      - Notebooks, holograph, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 111-112)
      - Chapters
        - "Prospectus," draft, typescript, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 113)
        - "Why I Did It?: The Blow-Dried Kitten," multiple drafts, 1989-1990 (Box 9, Folder 114-115)
        - "Biting the Hand That Feeds Him," multiple drafts, 1989-1990 (Box 9, Folder 116)
        - "Bandit Himself," multiple drafts, accompanied by cover letter from Hearne to Joy Johannessen dated "1991 January 31 and beyond", 1989-1991, undated (Box 9, Folder 117)
        - "This Isn't an Animal Rights Case, Professor Wizner," multiple drafts, 1990, undated (Box 9, Folder 118)
        - "My Dog: The Naming of Rights," draft, typescript, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 119)
        - "Neuter Alice," multiple drafts, 1989, undated (Box 9, Folder 120)
        - "The Rap Sheet," draft, typescript, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 121)
        - Drafts with editor's comments and proofreader's marks
          - [1] Preliminary draft, undated (Box 9, Folder 122-126)
          - [2] Response to edited copy, undated (Box 10, Folder 127-131)
          - [3] Response to edited copy #2, with paste-ups of preliminary pages accompanied by internal publisher's note, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 132-138)
      - Index, master proof, undated (Box 10, Folder 139)
      - Book cover art, undated (Box 10, Folder 140)
      - National "Pit Bull Terrier" Defense Association Newsletter, 1988-1989 (Box 11, Folder 141-143)
      - Typescript of " Bandit: Dossier of a Dangerous Dog Prolegomena" prepared for a reading for Literacy Volunteers, 1991 Aug 17 (Box 11, Folder 144)
      - News releases and press kits, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 145-146)
      - Publicity photographs, undated (Box 11, Folder 147)
      - Press clippings, 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 148)
      - Reviews, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 149)
    - First Friend
      - Book proposal for "First Friend: The Cultures of the Dog," typescript, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 150)
      - Notebook, holograph, undated (Box 11, Folder 151)
      - Chapters
        - Prologue, draft, typescript, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 152)
        - [Introductory chapter], draft, typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 153)
        - "Chapter 1: Always and Always and Always," multiple drafts, undated (Box 11, Folder 154)
        - "Chapter 1: Real Friends Now," multiple drafts, 2001, undated (Box 11, Folder 155)
        - "Chapter 2: Laying Waste to the Dogs of the Gods," draft, typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 156)
    - Horse Breaking: The Obedience Method, (co-authored with Bill Forest) typescript, with captioned photographs, undated (Box 12, Folder 157-160)
    - White German Shepherd
      - Contract with The Atlantic Monthly Press (two copies), 1987 (Box 12, Folder 161)
      - Early draft of chapters 1-9 from ring-binder, annotated typescript, with manuscript notes and various typescript pages of later drafts, undated (Box 12, Folder 162-163)
      - "Original" chapter one, multiple drafts, undated (Box 12, Folder 164)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, with holograph notes, "from brown notebook", undated (Box 12, Folder 165)
      - Draft, typescript, corrected, with holograph notes, "from blue notebook", undated (Box 12, Folder 166)
      - Draft, typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 167-169)
      - Draft, typescript, with annotations in an unidentified hand, 1987 June 1 (Box 13, Folder 170-172)
      - Draft, typescript, "final [draft], July 15, 1987", 1987 July 15 (Box 13, Folder 173-175)
      - Draft, typescript with editor's annotations and proofreaders' marks, undated (Box 13, Folder 176-179)
      - Uncorrected advance proof, bound, [1988?] (Box 14, Folder 180)
      - Royalty statements, 1988-1990 (Box 14, Folder 181)
      - Atlantic Monthly Press catalog, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 182)
      - Reviews, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 183)
      - Publisher's Weekly interview with Hearne, 1988 April 22 (Box 14, Folder 184)
  - Articles and Presentations
    - "And Yet We Find Her Beautiful," drafts, typescript, corrected, with email between Hearne and Jim Hearne, 1998-1999 (Box 14, Folder 185-188)
    - "Animal Instincts," columns, printed versions, published in Northeast: Hartford Courant Sunday Magazine, 1993 October 31, Nov 7 (Box 14, Folder 189)
    - "Animals" column, printed version, published in the Los Angeles Times Magazine 1985 Oct 6- Dec 15; 1986 Jan 5-Jun 8, 1985-1986 (Box 14, Folder 190-193)
    - "Animals in Law Enforcement," draft, typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 194)
    - "Anthropomorphism: Thinking Through Animals and Others,"draft, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 15, Folder 195)